Hello, and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're going
to be learning how to draw zwitterions,
which are different structures for
amino acids, and we're going to be
looking at them in different pHs.
So exactly, let's go through it, let's
look at what an amino acid is, and
try to understand what the basic idea
of a zwitterion is, and some tips and
tricks behind how to draw these for
your introductory biochemistry course.
So for what we're going to be starting
with is just looking at a normal amino
acid here and What we got to realize is
that it does not actually exist like this
when it is in a physiological condition
Meaning when it's in the body because
your body is full of solutions, right?
It's essentially we are
one giant bag of liquid.
So if we were to look at this, right?
We have a couple different things
we want to label We have our
carboxylic acid side of the amino
acid, which is our C terminal.
We have our amino acid side,
which is on the left hand side,
so we have our amino acid.
That is known as an N terminal.
We have our R group as well,
which is generally very special
for every one of the 20 amino
acids that we find in the body.
And where that R group is located
is on what we call the alpha carbon.
So every single amino acid occurs in
that order from left to right is an amino
acid on the left, on that left hand side.
or the left hand side, and then it
goes NCC every time, right, NCC, NCC.
As they're bonding in those
proteins, right, it's going
to make a polypeptide chain.
Now what does it mean if it's, how
do we look at this in the body?
Well, if we have this structure
here, what is going to be changing?
Well, what do acids and bases do?
Well, to kind of review that a little
bit, right, acids donate a proton.
So if we have that carboxylic acid side,
That is going to donate a proton, and it's
going to exist to look a little bit more
like this, where we're going to have a
negative charge on our carboxylate group.
And where's that hydrogen going to go?
Well, it needs to go to a base.
And where, well, how can
we label these two sides?
Well, if I have my acid side...
You also have your base side, right,
because amines are your organic bases.
So when that happens, it will accept
that extra proton, which will then give a
positive charge on our nitrogen group, a
negative charge on our carboxylic group,
creating what is known as a zwitter ion.
Now zwitter ions have two charges, so
one way for you to help remember two
charges is you think the word zwitter has
two Ts, right, so two Ts, two charges.
So that was one way a student
of mine told me to remember that
and it's, it can stick, right?
Those little things help.
So two charges, now as a result, those
two charges are overall neutral, okay?
So when we have that neutral charge,
because the positive cancels out
the negative, that is making an
overall zero charge as a result.
So we have a zero charge from that when we
have those two charges combining together.
So keep that in mind, right?
Neutral means zero overall.
Let's go through this and go
through some different examples of
how we can apply this, and let's
go look at some tips and tricks.
Alright, tips and tricks for these.
These are sometimes the most
complicated thing for introductory
students to draw, because assets and
bases are really hard to understand.
So one thing we have to realize is
that the physiological conditions
of your body vary depending
on where we are talking about.
Every organ has its own unique pH,
which breaks down different types of
chemicals through metabolism differently.
Now, as a result, we, one way to
remember how to draw these is think
of how acids and bases behave.
Acids donate protons, so, meaning
that they generally give them away.
So, what I want you to think of is
when we have an acid, Think about
adding H Now what do bases do?
Bases receive a proton.
So what does that mean that bases do?
They will remove H plus from something.
So when we're referring to the
different pHs of the physiological
body, if we are in a basic or a
high pH, we're removing an H plus.
And if we're in a low pH, then
we are going to be adding H plus.
Okay, so low and high pH.
Now what is that all in res in essentially
in respect to, well, if we have, let's
say, a Witter ion, well, we have to
think of how does the amino acid behave?
What does it consider a low and high?
Well, every amino acid has what
is known as an isoelectric point.
Now this is where essentially
it will be a zwitterion.
Every amino acid has its own unique value.
Now for the isoelectric point,
generally we'd label that as
PI whenever we are seeing that.
So where that zwitterion is
located, like the one that we have
here in the middle of the screen.
This is drawn as this ion,
meaning that the body's pH is
equal to its isoelectric point.
So how will that structure
change if I'm to go both ways?
So let's think of those tips from above.
Remember, add hydrogen.
Remove hydrogen.
So if I go, let's say on the,
um, the left hand side here.
Let's say if I want to be more acidic.
Well, what exactly is going
to happen to this structure?
Well, let's think.
So if I am to be at a lower pH, so
pH less than the PI, meaning I am
acidic, We are going to add hydrogen.
So where can you add an H plus?
What's the thing that most
likely wants to accept an H plus?
The negative area, right?
So when that happens, right, we're going
to add a hydrogen to that negative area.
Okay, so we're going
to put that right here.
Now, as a result, how
does the charge change?
You can see overall, the
charge is equal to...
plus one as a result.
So when that is an acidic condition,
we can see that as a plus one.
Now, if we want to go the other way,
let's say if I want to go basic in
this case, well, same idea here, is
we're going to be removing H plus.
So where can you remove H plus
from, from your zwitterion?
Where is it the easiest
to take that away from?
Well, as you can see, we have an
extra one on that amino group.
So, what are we going to do?
We're going to remove that, that plus
charge, take away a hydrogen, therefore
making a, um, an ion that is now
able to act like a base by removing.
When the pH is greater than the PI,
we now have a charge of negative
one, which is our structure.
Okay, so if you remember the acids
and bases, add H plus charge.
Remove H plus, it's gonna
make it a lot easier.
So let's take a look at some different
examples and see if we can practice
this and master this together.
Okay, so now in the following example,
what are we going to be doing?
Well, this says draw the structure of
lysine at the following phs and the PI is
equal to 9.7, meaning that the isoelectric
point for this amino acid that's
drawn here, this is what is considered
to be neutral for that amino acid.
So, if I have the amino acid here,
what exactly would it look like if
it was a physiological condition?
Well, that is where the
zwitterion will come into play.
So if I am going to have my zwitterion,
the first thing we've got to remember
is remember acids donate that proton.
So now when it does that, we are going to
have that negative charge on the O, and
that hydrogen is going to be added over
to that, um, that H3, and it's going to
put a positive charge on our nitrogen.
Where can we go first?
Let's fill in these different structures.
So if I want to go to, let's say,
a higher pH, right, so this is
considered to be basic conditions,
what would essentially happen?
So I'm at a pH of 12 here, where the pH is
a lot higher than that isoelectric point.
So base, we're removing hydrogen.
So where can I remove hydrogen from?
The only place that is available
is that amino group that is
on that, uh, side over here.
So we can remove it from that location.
So if I do that, right, it takes away
the charge, and as a result, we have
H2N, and that is a basic amino acid.
Let's go more acidic.
What if you start traveling
through the digestive tract
and things start to change?
So where, what will we first have
is we are now going more acidic.
So on these next two, you can see
it gets progressively more acidic.
Meaning that the farther and farther
you go, it could start changing more
and more throughout the structure.
The first place that we are going
to be doing acidic conditions
is, remember, is adding hydrogen.
So where can we add hydrogen first?
Well, right directly to the amino
backbone, where the amino group,
the carboxylic acid group is.
So we are going to add a hydrogen to the
one place that is possible, and that's
going to be right on that carboxylic acid.
Being that the amino group already
has one, there's no room for
you to add one to that location.
Now, as this starts getting even
more and more acidic, so if I
take this thing, is there anywhere
else that we can add a hydrogen?
And the one thing you're always
looking at, are there any amino
groups that we can add this to?
And if you look at the ARD group, all the
way at the bottom, that's on both these
sides here, This is a basic amino acid,
meaning that eventually, if you keep
lowering that pH, we will add a hydrogen
down below with another charge down
here, and that is going to, once again,
add a hydrogen into another location.
So we can see, as it travels from basic
to what is considered neutral with the
isoelectric point, all the way to acidic,
the charges are changing as a result.
And we can even write down
the charges here, right?
We see that goes from negative 1
to neutral, positive 1 to positive
2, uh, overall, as we go from one
structure to the next to the next.
Let's do one more together.
So this was a basic example.
Let, and the first one that
we did together was neutral.
Let's take a look at an acidic amino acid.
Okay, let's draw the structure of
aspartic acid at the following pH.
Which has a 0, which is
where it's considered being
neutral for this amino acid.
So this is aspartic acid.
This is an acidic amino acid, and
right here what I do, what I already
have drawn for us is a zwitterion.
So let's first go in the acidic direction.
So if I were to go to the acidic
direction, what can change?
Well, remember, acid is
adhydrogen, AA, right?
If I add hydrogen, Where
can you add an H plus two?
Well, if we're going to look
at these groups, is there
anywhere available for us?
And the one place you can see is
right on that negative charge,
right here on that carboxylic acid.
So if I add an H plus, we can see
the overall charge as a result
turns to plus one when we do that.
So we are adding our hydrogen.
Now, what happens if I start going
Basic, well, if we start going from
one basic molecule to the other,
the whole idea is the farther you
get basic where you want to remove
hydrogens from the different locations.
Now exam questions and things like
that can change depending on how your
teacher ends up wording it, right?
Um, sometimes they might just want
the final thing, usually that's what I
ask for for my students, but everyone,
it's always about removing H pluses.
So, where can I remove H plus first?
The first place is that amino
backbone, being that we have
that positive charge, right?
So I'm going to remove one of those.
Uh, one of those hydrogens there,
and overall, then we have just
a negative one charge, right?
It goes from plus one to
neutral, negative one overall.
Now where can I remove it on the
next one as I keep increasing the pH?
Well, not only did I take
one off the backbone earlier.
But I can also remove one off the
carboxylic acid group, which is
down here at the bottom, right?
We have COOH, and when that happens,
we now have a negative ion that is
down here, meaning we have an overall
charge of 2 minus as a result.
Which then shows you how aspartic acid
can change to aspartate by removing
all those little pieces, right?
Because the 8 ending means assault.
So this is how you can go through these.
We went through a neutral example, an
acidic example, and a basic example.
I hope that this video helped you
and I hope you do well on your
homeworks and exams with this.
And if you did like this video, hit the
like button, subscribe to the channel,
and I hope to see you all in the future.
All right.
Bye now.